{"tossups": [{"question": "<em>This event killed the inspirational author Elbert Hubbard</em>. William Thomas Turner was criticized after this event for ignoring orders to maintain a zig-zag course off the Old Head of Kinsale. William Jennings Bryan resigned as Secretary of State in protest to Woodrow Wilson's response to this event, which prompted debate about a vessel's status as a legitimate military target. For 10 points, name this May 1915 event in which a British ocean liner was sunk by a U-boat.", "answer": "sinking of the RMS <em><b><u>Lusitania</u></b></em>  {I}", "metadata": "MC"}, {"question": "<em>This king earned his country land in the Treaty of Stolbovo, which ended the Ingrian War</em> <em>against Russia.</em> He continued a war that his father Charles IX started with Polish king Sigismund III. This leader scored a decisive victory against the Count of Tilly at Breitenfeld. While leading a cavalry charge, this king died at the Battle of Lutzen. For 10 points, name this \"Lion of the North,\" a Swedish king who fought in the Thirty Years' War.", "answer": "<b><u>Gustavus Adolphus</u></b> [or <b><u>Gustav II</u></b> Adolf]  {I}", "metadata": "JL"}, {"question": "<em>Each year at this location, Aladdin the Christmas Camel recreates a show put on by this</em> <em>place's owner</em>. Louise and Ann Cunningham were horrified to see this place in poor condition and formed a Ladies' Association to repair it. The owner of this place acquired a severe sore throat in the winter and was advised excessive bloodletting by his personal physicians, which helped kill him. For 10 points, name this Virginia plantation home of George Washington.", "answer": "<b><u>Mount Vernon</u></b>  {I}", "metadata": "MC"}, {"question": "<em>This island was once home to the Beothuk people.</em> The protagonist of <em>The Shipping News</em> by E. Annie Proulx (<b>pr. PROOL</b>) returns to this island. The first transatlantic wireless message traveled from England to this island's Signal Hill. This island is home to a former Viking settlement at L'Anse aux Meadows (<b>pr. LONS-oh Meadows</b>). The capital of the most recently incorporated Canadian province is this island's city of St. John's. For 10 points, name this island that composes a province with Labrador.", "answer": "<b><u>Newfoundland</u></b>  {I}", "metadata": "KG"}, {"question": "<em>Two days before this event, a look alike named Felix Dadaev (<b>pr. duh-DYE-ev</b>) was told to</em> <em>\"be ready to stand in\" if needed</em>. Jonathan Brent and Vladimir Naumov theorized that a secret police chief caused this event by slipping warfarin into a man's wine glass. It set up a power struggle featuring such men as Lavrenty Beria and former Foreign Affairs Minister Molotov, who both failed in their attempts to take over. For 10 points, name this 1953 death of a Soviet leader.", "answer": "The <b><u>death</u></b> of Joseph <b><u>Stalin</u></b> [or the <b><u>death</u></b> of Iosif Vissarionovich <b><u>Stalin</u></b>; or the <b><u>death</u> </b>of Ioseb Besarionis Dze <b><u>Jugashvili</u></b>], accept just \u201cStalin\u201d after \u201cdeath\u201d  {I}", "metadata": "MC"}, {"question": "<em>This non-Christian deity is Vasco da Gama's main supernatural helper in the Portugueseepic,</em> <em>the Lusiads.</em> In Ovid's Metamorphoses, this deity begs Jupiter to turn the murdered Julius Caesar into a star, since the historical Julii (<b>pr. JOO-lee-ee</b>) clan claimed descent from her. In another foundation myth, she presents a shield depicting future Roman history to her son, which she had requested from her husband Vulcan. For 10 points, name this mother of Aeneas, the Roman goddess of love.", "answer": "<b><u>Venus</u></b> [do not accept \"Aphrodite\"]  {I}", "metadata": "MJ"}, {"question": "<em>The president of the country targeted by this event delayed negotiations by traveling to</em> <em>Mauritius.</em> Following this event, Dora Bloch was killed at a hospital. Two members of the German Revolutionary Cells assisted in a hijacking ordered by Wadie Haddad that occurred a week before this event. Benjamin Netanyahu's brother Yonatan was killed during this event. For 10 points, identify this 1976 event in which Israeli forces rescued hostages from Uganda.", "answer": "<b><u>Entebbe</u></b> Raid [or Operation <b><u>Entebbe</u></b>; or Operation <b><u>Thunderbolt</u></b>]  {I}", "metadata": "KG"}, {"question": "<em>This man called Maya Lin an \u201cegg roll\u201d during the competition to design the Vietnam</em> <em>Memorial.</em> This man sponsored a group led by Arthur D. Simons, which rescued two employees of his company, Electronic Data Systems. During one speech, he urged his audience to listen for the \u201cgiant sucking sound\u201d caused by the signing of NAFTA. For 10 points, name his founder of the Reform Party and businessman who ran in the 1992 and 1996 presidential elections.", "answer": "Henry Ross <b><u>Perot</u></b>  {I}", "metadata": "EM"}, {"question": "<em>The last person to take a photo of this object in its entirety was Jack Schmidtt, who was</em> <em>accompanied by Eugene Cernan and Ronald Evans.</em> Carl Sagan titled the sequel to <em>Cosmos</em> for a photograph of this object. Another photograph taken by Bill Anders of this object is titled for its \"rise,\" and was taken during the first manned mission to orbit the moon. For 10 points, name this object photographed by Voyager 1 in \"Pale Blue Dot\" and by Apollo 17 in \"The Blue Marble.\"", "answer": "photographs of <b><u>Earth</u></b> [accept anything indicating the planet <b><u>Earth</u></b>; prompt on <b><u>planet</u></b> or <b><u>world</u></b>]", "metadata": "Science - Other Science - Astronomy"}, {}, {"question": "<em>The Pierce Patent made this document no longer necessary.</em> This document was most likely written by William Brewster and was intended to settle differences between the \"Strangers\" and the \"Saints.\" Although its original is lost, it was copied in William Bradford's journal and reprinted in <em>Of Plymouth Plantation</em>. For 10 points, what 1620 document established a \"civil body politic\" out of the group that had come to America on the namesake ship?", "answer": "<b><u>Mayflower Compact</u> </b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<em>This event was preceded by the Address of the 221</em>. It was prompted by the publishing in \u201cLe Moniteur\u201d of the Ordinances of St. Cloud, which dissolved the Chamber of Deputies. An appeal to Jules de Polignac (<b>pr. pole-en-YACK</b>) failed during this event, which took place during the \u201cThree Glorious Days.\u201d It saw the capture of the Hotel de Ville and the creation of barricades. For 10 points, name this event in France which saw replacement of Charles X with Louis Philippe.", "answer": "<b><u>July</u></b> Revolution [or <b><u>July</u></b> Days; French Revolution of <b><u>1830</u></b>; accept <b><u>Three Glorious</u></b> <b><u>Days</u></b> until Three Glorious Days]", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "<em>This novel's second volume ends with a great comet overhead, which reminds the protagonist</em> <em>of the number 666.</em> This novel's Second Epilogue restates its many digressions claiming that the course of history does not depend on great men. In this novel, Prince Andrei serves in the army under General Kutuzov, who burns Moscow shortly before Pierre Bezukhov is taken prisoner in 1812. For 10 points, name this long novel about Napoleon's invasion of Russia, by Leo Tolstoy.", "answer": "<em><b><u>War and Peace</u></b></em> [or <em><b><u>Voyna i mir</u></b></em>]", "metadata": "Literature - European Literature - Long Fiction"}, {}, {"question": "<em>In a victory for this commander, his forces ambushed and pinned down those of Flaminius</em> <em>next to a body of water.</em> The Fabian strategy was first employed to slow this man's advances. After entering Italy, this general led forces to victory in the battles of Trebia and Lake Trasimene. This general's elephants were neutralized in a plan by Scipio Africanus that helped lead to his defeat at the Battle of Zama. For 10 points, name this Carthaginian general.", "answer": "<b><u>Hannibal</u></b> Barca", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {"question": "<em>Supporters of this group wore football helmets while vandalizing the Gold Coast</em> <em>neighborhood</em>. This group held the Flint War Council after organizing an attempt to \"bring the war home,\" the Days of Rage. Three members of this group were killed while making a nail bomb in Greenwich Village. This group took its name from a Bob Dylan lyric about \"which way the wind blows.\" For 10 points, name this militant left-wing group which operated during the Vietnam War.", "answer": "<b><u>Weathermen</u></b> [or <b><u>Weather Underground</u></b>]", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<em>This leader's ministers argued over whether to launch a punitive invasion in the Seikanron</em> <em>debate.</em> This leader promoted the slogan \"enrich the country, strengthen the military\" in place of the earlier <em>sonno joi</em> idea. Saigo Takamori rebelled against this leader in the Satsuma War, and this leader came to power by winning the Boshin War. For 10 points, name this westernizing Japanese emperor who ended the Tokugawa shogunate.", "answer": "<b><u>Meiji</u></b> Emperor", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "<em>This policy was partly a response to the concept of Calvo clauses and to the Drago Doctrine.</em> This policy was announced after a crisis in which Cipriano Castro refused to pay his country's debts. The Clark Memorandum repudiated this doctrine, which was replaced by the Good Neighbor Policy. For 10 points, name this key part of the \"big stick\" policy, an addition to the Monroe Doctrine proposed by Teddy Roosevelt.", "answer": "<b><u>Roosevelt Corollary</u></b> to the Monroe Doctrine [or Roosevelt <b><u>Corollary</u></b> after \"Roosevelt\" is read; prompt on \"Monroe Doctrine\"]", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<em><b><u>Tsar Paul sheltered many members of this group in 1798, and got them to declare him their</u></b></em> <em><b><u>leader rather than Ferdinand von Hompesch.</u></b></em><b><u> This group, led early on by Raymond de Puy,</u></b> <b><u>began around a building founded by Amalfi merchants. Pope (+)</u> Paschal II formally recognized this group, which was led by Jean de Valette after it relocated to Malta from the Suleiman-besieged island of (*)</b> Rhodes. Formally, its members venerated the man who baptized Jesus. For 10 points, name this non-Templar Crusader order founded to protect centers for healing the wounded.", "answer": "Knights <b><u>Hospitaler</u></b>s [or Order of the Knights of <b><u>St. John</u></b> of Jerusalem; accept Knights of <b><u>Malta</u></b> before \"Malta\"; accept Order of the Knights of <b><u>Rhodes</u></b> before \"Rhodes\"]  {I}", "metadata": "MJ"}, {"question": "<em><b><u>This man claimed an enemy moved \"with the perseverance of a mighty avalanche.\"</u> </b></em><b><u>This</u></b> <b><u>man was defended by Francis Scott Key after he assaulted Congressman William</u></b> <b><u>Stanberry. He suffered a bullet wound in his ankle prior to the signing of the Treaty of (+)</u></b> <b>Velasco. The only man to be elected governor of two different U.S. states, he was also the only Southern governor to oppose (*)</b> secession. He was succeeded as President by Mirabeau Lamar. For 10 points, name this first President of the Republic of Texas and namesake of the state's most populous city.", "answer": "Samuel \u201cSam\u201d <b><u>Houston</u></b>  {I}", "metadata": "MC"}, {"question": "<em><b><u>This man co-founded the micronation of Nutopia in response to the Nixon administration\u2019s</u></b></em> <em><b><u>efforts to deport him</u></b></em><b><u>. This man gave an interview with him and his wife entirely covered in</u></b> <b><u>a bag as a political statement. He sang \u201cwe gave her everything we owned just to sit at her</u></b> <b><u>(+)</u> table\u201d in a song critical of theMaharishi, \u201cSexy Sadie.\u201d During his honeymoon, he staged a \u201cbed-in\u201d in protest of the (*)</b> Vietnam War, and he was murdered three weeks after releasing <em>Double Fantasy</em> by a man upset that he once called his band \u201cbigger than Jesus,\u201d Mark David Chapman. For 10 points, name this Beatle who married Yoko Ono and sang \u201cImagine.\u201d", "answer": "John <b><u>Lennon</u></b>  {I}", "metadata": "CW"}, {"question": "<em><b><u>This policy was partly inspired by a volcanic eruption on Thera and the use of the</u></b></em> <em><b><u>Hodegetria during a siege.</u> </b></em><b><u>Opponents of this policy claimed that a king had defecated in his</u></b> <b><u>baptismal font, earning him the epithet \"copronymus.\" Riots over this policy began with</u></b> <b><u>an action at the Chalke gate. This policy was supported by the (+)</u>Council of Hieria, but condemned by the Second Council of Nicaea (</b>pr. nigh-SEE-uh<b>), which was called by (*) </b>Irene. This policy was begun by Leo III of the Isaurian dynasty. For 10 points, name this policy which called for the destruction of Byzantine religious images.", "answer": "Byzantine <b><u>iconoclasm</u></b> [or word forms like <b><u>iconoclast</u></b>ic]", "metadata": "JB"}, {"question": "<em><b><u>This politician remarked: \u201cThis is not cojones (</u></b><u>pr. co-HO-nace</u><b><u>). This is cowardice\u201d after</u></b></em> <em><b><u>Cuban pilots shot down two planes flown by Brothers to the Rescue</u></b></em><b><u>. This politician</u></b> <b><u>articulated the \u201cthree Ds of NATO\u201d and sparred with Boutros Boutros-Ghali as (+)</u> ambassador to the UN. This Czechoslovak-born politician succeeded WarrenChristopher and preceded</b> (*) Colin Powell in an office in whose tenure she made a high-profile visit to North Korea to meet with Kim Jong-Il. For 10 points, name this first female Secretary of State, a member of President Bill Clinton\u2019s Cabinet.", "answer": "Madeleine <b><u>Albright</u></b> [or Madeleine Jana Korbel <b><u>Albright</u></b>; or Marie Jana <b><u>Korbelova</u></b>]  {I}", "metadata": "AG"}, {"question": "<em><b><u>This artist painted several depictions of a hunter and his dog in the first of his tapestry</u></b></em> <em><b><u>cartoons.</u> </b></em><b><u>This artist created multiple works in which dismembered body parts are stuck on</u></b> <b><u>tree branches, and others in which soldiers attempt to sexually assault women. Another of</u></b> <b><u>his works shows a diagonal line of hatted (+)</u>soldiers standing near a box lantern that casts light on the central figure. This creator of the </b><em><b>Disasters of War</b></em><b> etching series also (*) </b>unflatteringly painted his patron, Charles IV of Spain. For 10 points, name this creator of a painting in which a man assumes a Christ-like pose in front of a firing squad on <em>The 3rd of May,</em> <em>1808.</em>", "answer": "Francisco Jose de <b><u>Goya</u></b> y Lucientes  {I}", "metadata": "AK"}, {"question": "<em><b><u>Following one of these events, the emissary Suh Chan was beheaded.</u></b></em><b><u> During one of these</u></b> <b><u>events, Hong Dagu chose to attack before reinforcements traveling from Zhousan Island</u></b> <b><u>arrived. Fan Wenhu and much of a defeated Song army was pressed into service for the (+)</u> second of these conflicts. A series of scrolls about these conflicts, commissioned by Takezaki Suenaga, included a depiction of a</b> (*) landing on northern Kyushu. For 10 points, what 1274 and 1281 invasions were stopped by typhoons known as kamikaze?", "answer": "<b><u>Mongol invasions</u></b> of <b><u>Japan</u></b> [or <b><u>Kublai Khan</u></b>\u2019s <b><u>invasions</u></b> of <b><u>Japan</u></b>; or obvious equivalents mentioning <b><u>Japan</u></b> being under attack by <b><u>Mongol</u></b>s]  {I}", "metadata": "DW"}, {"question": "<em><b><u>Carles Haughey\u2019s photographs of this conflict are collected in \u201cA Weather Walked in\u201d.</u> </b></em><b><u>In</u></b> <b><u>one image of this conflict, a man with a plaid shirt and his arms behind his back has a</u> (+) gun pointed at his head Nick Ut took a Pulitzer-winning photograph of this war in which five small</b> (*) children, one a completely naked girl, run down a road towards the viewer as smoke rises in the background. Early in this war, Malcolm Browne took a picture of a monk burning himself to protest Ngo Dinh Diem's crackdown on Buddhists. For 10 points, name this war whose end led to photographs of American helicopters leaving a country reunified under Communism.", "answer": "<b><u>Vietnam</u></b> War", "metadata": "MJ"}, {"question": "<em><b><u>This woman came into conflict with a relative advised by Pothinus during an inheritance</u></b></em> <em><b><u>dispute</u></b></em><b><u>. This woman had her sister Arsinoe (</u></b><u>pr. ar-SIN-oh-ay</u><b><u>) killed at the Temple of</u></b> <b><u>Artemis, and she supposedly drank a pearl dissolved in (+)</u>vinegar as part of a bet. This ruler met one future lover while rolled up in a (*)</b> carpet, and her children received the Donations of Alexandria. This person supposedly committed suicide by getting bitten by a snake. For 10 points, name this late Greco-Egyptian queen, the lover of Julius Caesar and Marc Antony.", "answer": "<b><u>Cleopatra</u></b> VII Philopator  {I}", "metadata": "JZ"}], "bonuses": []}